gaier adam





agaier





+49-15773666037

agaier.github.io

education

phd | computer science inria, university of lorraine (fr)| 2016-2020 (expected)

- research: design exploration, evolutionary computation, bayesian optimization
- advisor: Jean-Baptiste Mouret

msc | autonomous systems bonn-rhein-sieg university (de)| 2012-2019

 research: robotics, evolutionary optimization, neuroevolution, data-efficient optimization

msc | evolutionary and adaptive systems

university of sussex (uk)| 2011-2012

 research: biologically-inspired computation, insect intelligence, neuroevolution, hypernetworks

bsc | computer science richmond american international university in london (uk)|

 research: species-conserving genetic algorithms for design

awards

2002-2005

- Best Paper Award 2018
 Genetic and Evolutionary
 Computation Conference
- Best Paper Award 2017 Genetic and Evolutionary Computation Conference
- Best Paper Award 2017 AIAA Multidisciplinary Analysis and Optimization Conference
- **Drive-E Studienpreis** 2015 National award for outstanding work in the electric mobility
- Pegge Scholarship 2011
 High potential Evolutionary and Adaptive Systems student

overview

Nomadic American researcher with an eclectic background and research experience spanning **evolutionary computation**, **robotics**, and **machine learning**. Deep background in biologically-inspired computation, focused on **neuroevolution**, diversity, and **novelty-based approaches**. Concentrated on **integration of evolutionary and ML** techniques in doctoral research – with particular application to **real-world design** and control problems. Fascinated by questions of creativity, embodiment, and innateness in machine intelligence.

experience

google brain (tokyo, japan) 2019

| research intern

- developed methods to evolve weight agnostic neural networks (WANN) architectures which perform with random weights (weightagnostic.github.io/) %
- published general-purpose neuroevolution tool %

inria (nancy, france)

| doctoral researcher

2015 - present

- developed approach to combine Bayesian optimization and quality-diversity techniques for design exploration in computationally expensive domains
- published source code of approach (Surrogate-Assisted Illumination) applied to aerodynamic optimization %
- improved data-efficiency of state-of-the-art neuroevolution algorithms by integrating machine learning techniques into the evolutionary process
- analyzed ability of quality-diversity techniques to tackle problems in highly deceptive objective spaces

bonn-rhein-sieg university (bonn, germany) | research associate 2012 - present

- developed techniques for aerodynamic design optimization and exploration
- evolved neural network controllers for terrain-aware fuel efficient vehicle control
- designed and taught masters level courses on evolutionary computation

tsinghua international school (beijing, china) | cs department head 2009 - 2011

- created school-wide CS curriculum for new K-12 international school
- taught CS courses to 7th to 12th grade students of mixed language abilities

various (beijing, china) | bartender, poker player, restaurant manager 2006 - 2010

Worked as a bartender, sound engineer, and musician at underground rock venue D-22 while supporting myself playing poker. Managed the Kro's Nest, a pizza place with all Chinese staff, becoming marketing lead when the restaurant became a chain.

- learned Chinese as a bartender, musician, and restaurant manager
- developed grit, mental resilience, and self-management skills as a poker player
- honed graphic design skills creating ads as marketing lead of a restaurant chain